<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine acts particularlie recommended by our most gratious and sacred soveraine to the Estates of Parliament of the Kingdome of Scotland, and by them, after graue and mature advisement and deliberation hartilie imbraced, concluded: and the 20. day of Iune 1609. inacted to stand for perpetuall lawes in all time to come: with most humble thanks to God for so wise &amp; carefull a prince and ruler, and most earnest prayer for His most excellent Majesties long raigne in all prospetitie [sic]..</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>Scotland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21892.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95076</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572930</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181030</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181030)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2155:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine acts particularlie recommended by our most gratious and sacred soveraine to the Estates of Parliament of the Kingdome of Scotland, and by them, after graue and mature advisement and deliberation hartilie imbraced, concluded: and the 20. day of Iune 1609. inacted to stand for perpetuall lawes in all time to come: with most humble thanks to God for so wise &amp; carefull a prince and ruler, and most earnest prayer for His most excellent Majesties long raigne in all prospetitie [sic]..</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>Scotland.</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Charteris, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majestie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' device on t.p. (McK. 307α).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D².</note>
                  <note>"Cum Privilegio Regiæ Majestatis."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Politics and government --  1371-1707 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAINE ACTS PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularlie recommended by our moſt GRATIOVS AND SACRED SOVERAINE TO THE E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Parliament of the Kingdome of Scotland, and by them, after graue and mature adviſement and deliberation hartilie imbraced, concluded: and <hi>the</hi> 20. <hi>day of Iune</hi> 1609.
<hi>inacted to ſtand for perpetuall lawes in all time to</hi> come: with moſt humble thanks to God for ſo wiſe &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>a Prince and Ruler, and moſt earneſt prayer for his moſt</hi> Excellent Majeſties long raigne in all proſpetitie.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>KYSTITIA. SVVM CVIQVE</p>
               <p>RELIGIO. DEVM COLE</p>
               <p>HIS SVFFVL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TA DVRANT.</p>
               <p>H C</p>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>PRINTED AT EDINBVRGH BY ROBERT CHAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie. 1609.</p>
            <p>Cum Privilegio Regiae Majeſtatis.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:2"/>
            <head>Act anent chooſing of Pedagoges to children paſsing fourth of Scotland to ſchooles.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as our Soveraine Lord and Eſtates of this preſent Parliament Conſidering that one of the great cauſſes which hes procured the grouth and increaſe of Papiſts within this kingdome hes proceeded from the ſmall care and regarde that hes bene had of the educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vpbringing of the youth, who being ſent forth of the realme to places of contrarie profeſſion, and not being firſt well grounded in religion, and accompanied with Pedagoges ſcarce well affected to religion, they doe often returne back ſo poſſeſt with ſuperſtition and hereticall errors, as they may be juſtlie ſuſpected for dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſubjects in the eſtate. For preventing of which grouth and increaſe of defection from the trew faith by the occaſion foreſaid, Our ſaid Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Lord and Eſtates foreſaids, Ordaines that all ſuch Noble men and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who hereafter ſhall direct anie Pedagoges with their ſonnes out of the countrie, ſhall be holden by vertew of this preſent Act, to haue a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent teſtimoniall of the Biſhop of the diocie where the ſaid Pedagoge for the moſt part latelie before made his reſidence: Teſtifying and approouing the ſaid Pedagoge to be godlie and of good religion, learned &amp; inſtructed in the ſame. And if anie Nole man or other ſhall happen to ſend anie Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagoge with their ſonnes out of the countrie without the teſtimoniall and approbation of the Biſhop in maner aboue written, In that cace our ſaide Soveraine Lord and Eſtates foreſaids Declares, ſtatutes and ordaines that everie ſuch Noble man and others according to their ſeverall degrees and ranks ſhall incur the paines particularlie vnderwritten, viz. everie Earle fiue thouſand pounds, everie Lord fiue thouſand marks, and everie barron three thouſand marks; which ſummes ſhalbe intrometted with &amp; vplifted of them by his Majeſties Theſaurer &amp; his depute to his Highnes vſe: Providing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cace it ſhal happen the Biſhop of that diocie to refuſe to grant teſtimonial to the Pedagoge vpon the premiſſes, the ſaid Biſhop thereafter being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie ſummoned to compeere before the Lords of his Highnes Secreete Counſell to anſwere to that complaint, and ſhow not a reaſonable cauſe of that his refuſall, Than and in that cace, it ſhall be lawfull to the Lords of ſecreet Counſell to giue their teſtimoniall to the foreſaid Pedagoge, to the effect aboue written.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:3"/>
            <head>Act againſt children that becomes papiſts when they are out of Scotland.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Soveraine Lord and Eſtates of this preſent Parliament Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines the Noblemen, Barons and others to haue a ſpeciall care and to giue order and direction that the remaining of their ſonnes forth of the countrie ſhall be in places where Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is profeſſed, or at the leaſt where there is no reſtraint of the ſame by the crueltie of Inquiſition: and that during the time of their abſence they ſhall not haunt any idolatrous exerciſe of religion, And that ſuch perſones as hes not the moyen to intertaine with their ſonnes a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagoge ſhall ſend them to ſuch places where religion is profeſſed. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cace their ſonnes after their departure out of the countrie ſhall haunt the exerciſes of contrarie religion, Our ſaid Soveraine Lord and Eſtates fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids ordaine that their parents or ſuch others as hes the charge of them ſhall be ſtraited to find caution acted in the bookes of ſecreet Counſel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch paines as ſhall be modified, that they ſhall not ſupplie, intertaine nor furniſh them with any thing neceſſare or comfortable vnto them after that it be knowne that their ſonnes are become papiſts and haunts Idolatry contrarie to the religion preſentlie profeſſed within Scotland, except their reſonable expenſſes in recalling and bringing them to this Realme of Scotland.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <head>Act anent exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate perſones not to inioy their lands, rowmes and poſſeſsions.</head>
            <p>OVr Soveraine Lord and Eſtates of this preſent Parliament Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that whereas there is divers perſones who are excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for not conforming themſelues to the trew religion preſently profeſſed, and do notwithſtanding ſtil injoy the poſſeſſions of their lands, rents and living<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eyther directlie in their owne perſons or covertlie in the perſons of their friends and wel-willers to their vſe &amp; behoofe, to the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of them to perſiſt in their pernitious and erroneous opinions, &amp; to the fruſtrating of the execution of the acts and conſtitutions made againſt excommunicants heretofore. Therefore our ſaid Soveraine Lord and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates foreſaids Declares, ſtatutes and ordaines That no perſons whatſoever who are alreadie or hereafter ſhall happen to be excommunicate for not conforming themſelues to the Religion preſentlie profeſſed within this kingdome, ſhall be ſuffered eyther directlie in their own perſons, or covert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and indirectlie by any others in their names and to their behooſe, injoy the poſſeſſion of their lands, rents and revenewes, But that the ſame ſhalbe medled with, intrometted with and vplifted to his Maieſties vſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:3"/>
            <head>Act giuing command to Biſhops to ſend the names of excommunicate perſones to the Theſaurer and to the Director of the Chancellarie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Soveraine Lord and Eſtates of this Preſent Parliament conſidering that to the effect everie mans affection &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in his religion may be clearly and ſufficiently kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wne, Therefore our ſaid Soveraine Lord and eſtates fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids Satutes and ordaines that everie Arch biſhop and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop within the bounds of his owne diocie ſhall once eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie yeere giue vp to the Theſaurer, Comptroller, Collector and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, and to the Director of our Soveraine Lords Chancellarie, a Roll ſubſcriued with his hand containing the names of all ſuch perſones within his diocie who are excommunicate for religion, and ordaines the ſaid The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurer and his deputes that they receiue no reſignations nor grant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations nor infeftments to nor in favors of anie of the perſones whoſe names ſhall be contained in the ſaid Roll: And that the Director of the Chancellarie and his deputes giue out no breeues, receiue no retoures, nor direct no precept vpon retoures, nor vpon compryſings in favors of any of the ſaids perſones whoſe names ſhall be inſert in the ſaid Roll at no time thereafter, while the ſaid perſone or perſones produce vnto the ſaid The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurer, Comptroller, Director of the Chancellarie and their deputes a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient teſtimonial ſubſcriued by the ſaid Archibiſhop or Biſhop, teſtifying their relaxation from the ſaid excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and their obedience and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the Kirk, as the ſaid Theſaurer, Director of the Chancellarie and their deputes will be anſwerable to his Maieſtie vppon the dewtie of their office. And likewiſe our ſaid Soveraine Lord and Eſtates foreſaids De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares that it ſhall be lawfull to all Lords of Regalities and to all ſuperiors whatſomever within this Kingdome, To refuſe breeues and preceptes of clare-conſtat in favors of anie perſon or perſons whoſe names ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert in the ſaid Roll: As alſo to refuſe the entrie of Tennents vppon compry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, whoſe names are inſert in the ſame Roll.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <head>Act againſt Ieſuites, Seminarie Preefts and reſetters of them.</head>
            <p>OVR Soveraine Lord and Eſtates of this preſent Parliament Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the impunitie of Ieſuites, Seminarie Preeſts and other papiſts adverſaries to the trew Religion profeſſed in this realme, and their reſetters in times bygone, hes bene the cauſe as well of their increaſe as of their inſolence in all the parts of this realme, And that the ſame hes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded partlie vppon the negligent execution of the Actes of Parliament made againſt the ſaid Papiſts, Ieſuites and Seminarie Preeſtes and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetters, <pb facs="tcp:181030:4"/>and partlie vpon ſome obſcuritie of words in the ſaids acts. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſaid ſoveraine Lord and Eſtates foreſaids moſt willing to haue the ſaids acts put to dew execution in all points, and Papiſtrie and ſuperſtition vtterly ſuppreſſed according to the intention of the ſame, Hes ratified, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and confirmed, and by the tenor of this preſent act Ratifies, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues &amp; confirmes all &amp; whatſomever acts of Parliament, eyther made in his Highnes minoritie and leſſe age, or elſe ſince his acceptation of the gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement in his own perſon, againſt Ieſuites, Seminarie Prieſts, Papiſts, ſayers &amp; hearers of Maſſe &amp; reſetters of the ſaids perſons or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; decerns and ordaines the ſame to haue full ſtrength, force and effect, and to be put to dew execution in all time comming with theſe explanations after fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, That the ſaids acts made againſt hearers and ſayers of maſſe ſhalbe put to dew execution, and be extended to all hearers and ſayers of Maſſe, without any exception or reſtriction. As likewaies that all acts made of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt the reſetters of the ſaids perſons haue their full force, ſtrength and effect, and be put to dew execution againſt the ſaid reſetters, after law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full intimation and denunciation be made of the ſaids perſons: which denu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation and intimation his Highnes and the eſtates foreſaids declares to be ſufficient to cauſe the ſaids reſetters of the ſaids Papiſts, Ieſuites, Seminarie Prieſts and others conteined in the ſaids acts, Incur the paines therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, if the ſame be made at the head burgh of the ſhyre where the ſaids perſons remaines, and at the mercat croſſe of Edinburgh, without anie far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intimation to be made thereanent. After the which denunciation and Intimation to be made, as ſaide is, Our ſaid Soveraine Lord and Eſtates foreſaids Declares that who ſoever thereafter ſhall wittinglie &amp; willinglie reſet anie of the ſaids perſones, eyther privatlie or publictlie, that the ſaids reſetters ſhall incur the paines conteined in the ſaids acts, they being law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie convict thereof. And that the act made in his Highnes firſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, bearing that none that profeſſe not the trew religion preſentlie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed within this realme may be Iudge, Procurator or member of court, Be extended to all and whatſomever offices, without any exception or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction in all time comming. And for the better execution of the ſaids acts Our ſaid Soveraine Lord and Eſtates foreſaids Commands &amp; ordaines all Arch-biſhops, Biſhops and Presbytries to call before them the ſaids pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, Ieſuites, Seminarie Prieſts and their reſetters, everie one within their owne bounds, And to take tryall and cognition if they haue contraveened the ſaids acts or anie part thereof, And according as they finde after dewe tryall and probation That they report the ſame to his Highnes Advocate and ſecreete counſell, To the effect they may be called and conveened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and puniſhed according to the ſaids acts in all points.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:4"/>
            <head>Act of the Commiſſariates and iuriſdiction giuen to Arch-biſhops &amp; Biſhops.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Soverain Lord vnderſtanding that in all wel gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned republicks, the iuriſdiction civil &amp; eccleſiaſtick are ſeverall, diſtinct &amp; divers iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which oght to be adminiſtrat by the perſons to whom the ſame properly belongs: and according to his Highnes moſt loving &amp; princely affection borne alwaies to the chriſtian refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church within this realme, beeing moſt willing that the ſaid Church ſhould brook and ioiſe their liberties, priviledges, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and iuriſdiction granted vnto them by his Maieſtie (from whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie their temporall iuriſdiction doth flow) and in that regarde belonging to them as being one of the eſtates of Parliament moſt neceſſare to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained for giving of their adviſe, counſell and aſſiſtance in all his Maieſties great and weightie affaires, Hes with expreſſe adviſe and conſent of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of Parliament reſtored and redintegrate the Arch biſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of this Realme to their former authoritie, dignitie, prorogatiue, privi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledges and iuriſdictions lawfullie pertaining and ſhal be known to pertaine to them (alwaies flowing from his Maieſtie, aſwell as anie other ordinar iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction doth) and ſpeciallie to the iuriſdiction of commiſſariates and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of iuſtice by their commiſſioners and deputies in all ſpirituall and eccleſiaſtical cauſes contraverted betwene any perſones dwelling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds &amp; diocees of their prelacies and biſhopricks: with ful power to the ſaids Arch-biſhops, Biſhops and their ſucceſſors in all time hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to nominate &amp; creare ſufficient, wiſe diſcreet and learned men, beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the law and practick of this realme, to ſerue and adminiſtrate iuſtice in the ſaids places of iudicatorie, to conſtitute clarks and all other vnder-officers ſo oft as the ſame ſhal valk by dimiſſion, deceaſe, deprivation or otherwaies, and to provide others in their places with as great freedome and libertie as anie Arch-biſhops or Biſhops in this realme formerlie hes done: Which commiſſares to be nominate and create by them ſhall iudge and decide in all cauſſes belonging to their iudicatorie: and wherein the commiſſares preſentlie in office are in vſe to decide, keeping the ſame ſtyle and forme which is preſentlie obſerved, and that manner of proceeding which ſhall be preſcrived and inioyned to them by ſpeciall iniunctiones without anie alteration of the preſent lawes or introduction of new and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth practicks vpon the ſubiects and lieges, and ſhall haue power of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of teſtaments every one of them within their own bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, the quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes thereof to be payed to the Arc-hbiſhops, Biſhops, their chamberlaines, factors and vnder-receivers appointed by them. For the better affectuating whereof his Maieſtie and eſtates of Parliament ordaines letters of horning <pb facs="tcp:181030:5"/>to be given and granted by the Lords of Seſſion in that ſame verie ſort that the Commiſſares preſent hes it, for executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al their ſentences &amp; decrets which ſhall happen to be pronounced by them, &amp; compelling of perſones to enter and confirme the teſtaments of their defuncts in the very ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that formerlie hes bene done. And for maintaining all things in better order and the reſtraining of vnlawfull divorcements, too frequentlie pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed within this realme, to the high diſhonor of God and ſlander of trew Religion: His Maieſtie with adviſe and conſent foreſaid hes ſtatute and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that in the burgh of Ediburgh there ſhal be reſident alwaies foure Commiſſares, two to be nominate and appoynted by the Arch-biſhop of Sanctandrois, and two by the Arch-biſhop of Glaſgow, who ſhal haue the onley power to decide in all cauſſes of divorcement, As likewiſe ſhal haue power of reduction of all decreets pronounced by any other Commiſſares to the hurt and prejudice of any of the lieges: before whom it ſhal be one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawfull to intend and perſew reductions of inferiour Commiſſares their ſentences and decretes
<hi>in prima inſtantia.</hi> And incace the ſaids Commiſſares to be appointed by the Arch-biſhops of Sanctandrois and Glaſgow, as ſaid is, performe not their duetie, the Lords of Seſſion ſhall haue power to try, cognoſce and determine in the ſame, and ſhall iudge vpon all decreets and ſentences alledged to be wrongouſlie pronounced by them: And that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are his Maieſties great Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtory, to whom his highnes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> adviſe of the ſaids eſtates, Giues &amp; grants an high &amp; ſupreme commiſſion for all ſuch cauſſes, to iudge and determine of them in ſuch caces: And declares that it ſhall be lawfull to the ſaids Lords of Counſell and Seſſion To advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate cauſſes to themſelues from anie of the Commiſſares, vpon iuſt &amp; law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full complaints made to them by anie of the ſubiects, and not otherwaies. Provyding alwaies that the ſaid Seſſion ſhall ever be readie to giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to his Maieſtie that their advocations haue beene grounded vpon probable and lawfull grounds for the well of the ſubiects. And that this foreſaid act may be put in preſent effect, his Maieſtie with adviſe foreſaid declares all former erections of Commiſſariates to be ſuppreſſed &amp; extinct from this foorth and for ever, all conſtitutions that haue beene in former tyme of the ſame in what ſoever part of the realme the ſame hath bene ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and by what ſoever manner the ſame hes proceded, acts of parliament ſecreet counſell and others made thereanent. And in like maner diſcharges and annulles all preſentations, gifts or diſpoſitions made by his Highnes to the Commiſſares preſent, or to any other concerning the ſaid commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariates, and al rights acquired by them by deceaſe, dimiſſion, or how ſoever the ſame hes vaicked, and all gifts and diſpoſitions made in favors of their Clarks and members of court, by whatſomever manner or order the ſame hes proceeded. With this proviſion alwaies, that the Commiſſares pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie in office, their clarks and other members of court, who ſhall be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized <pb facs="tcp:181030:5"/>with teſtimoniall from the Lords of Seſſion of their ſufficiency &amp; qualification to their ſeverall places and offices, ſhall brooke and joiſe the ſame, they alwaies receiving a newe preſentation and gift of their offices from the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops of their dyoſies where they ſerue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene and the firſt day of December next to come: Otherwaies if incace the ſaids Commiſſares and other members of court doe not produce the foreſaid Teſtimoniall from the Lord of Seſſion, as ſaid is, It ſhal be lawfull to the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops to provide other ſufficient perſons to the ſaids places, The reſtitution of the ſaid juriſdiction alwaies to be with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe reſervation of his Highnes and his ſucceſſors their prerogatiues and ſupremacy in all cauſſes eccleſiaſticall and civill within this realme. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding alwaies that this preſent act ſhall no waies be hurtfull nor prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to the heritable right of the commiſſariate within the bounds of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle pertaining to Archebald now Earle of Argyle, but the ſame to ſtand in the ſame force, ſtrength and effect as it was before this preſent act, And notwithſtanding thereof or anie clauſe therin contened <hi>Prout de iure.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <head>Act of the Commiſsioners of the peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as among the infinite monuments and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his Maieſties trew pietie, ſingulare wiſdome ſinceere zeale to juſtice and fatherly care of his people, the eſtates of this Kingdome haue not found any bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing more deſerved commendation and permanent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne to his Maieſtie, or greater profit, quyetnes and comfort to his Subiects, nor his conſtant perſeverance in his moſt religious and prudent reſolution to extirpate the vngodlie bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and brutall cuſtome of deadlie feeds, which by the inveterate abuſe of manie bypaſt ages was become ſo frequent in this realme, as the ſubiects of greateſt rank and qualitie vppon everie naughtie occaſion of baſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthie contraverſies of neighborhoode, for turves, fold-dykes, furres or marches of lands, fooliſh words or drunken diſcords betweene their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſervants and dependers, and anie other in the countrie, did ſo readilie embrace the protection of their vnjuſt and vnneceſſarie quarrelles, as did manie times involue themſelues and their whole friendſhip in moſt bloudy and mortall troubles, which they did proſecute with ſuch malice and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie, as to the extreme perrell of their ſoules, infame of their memoriall, and overthrow of their owne and their adverſaries houſes, Did diſtract the kingdome in oppoſite factions, and manie times furniſhed matter of moſt pernitious, ſeditious and civill warres. The inconveniences whereof being manifeſtlie ſeene and ſenſiblie felt both by the Princes and people of this <pb facs="tcp:181030:6"/>realme in many bypaſt ages and earneſtly ſoght to haue bene remoued, yet the corruption was ſo vniverſall, that the greateſt part prevailing againſt the beſt, that cruell barbaritie had both continuance and daylie increaſe, vntill his Maieſtie bending the excellent wiſdome and rare graces of his royall minde (wherewith God hes endewed him more aboundantlie then any King that ever did raigne in this Iland) againſt that godleſſe, vnnatural and beaſtlie-cuſtome, did deviſe and eſtabliſh a moſt godlie, juſt and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent law and ordinance for the courſe to be obſerved, for removing vpon equitable and iuſt conditions the deadlie feeds, which then ſtood in great number betweene the moſt powerfull ſubiects in this kingdome and their kinſmen, aſſiſters and partakers: In the execution whereof, God having mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſlie aſſiſted his Maieſties moſt holy &amp; iuſt intention, after exceding great care and paines taine by his Maieſtie in tryall of the originall cauſes of the ſaids diſcords, the trew circumſtances of the injuries and loſes ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by eyther party, and in preſcriving dew ſatisfaction to be indifferentlie made for redreſſe of al bypaſt harmes and wrongs, his Maieſties admirable conſtancie hes ſo overcome all difficulties, that the whole knowen feeds within the kingdome being now removed by perfite reconciliation, &amp; iuſt contentment of all parties having intereſt therein, his Maieſties whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects finds ſuch ioy and happines in the ſweet fruites of his wiſdome and providence expreſſed in that cace, That they earneſtlie wiſh that his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie who hes ſo carefully exterminate that abhominable peſt of deadlie feeds, may in his ſingulare wiſdome finde meanes for ever to prevent the reviuing of that monſter. Wherein his Maieſtie confidering that nothing gaue ſo great grouth and ſtrength to that bypaſt barbaritie as the ſlouth of magiſtrates in not ſuppreſſing the firſt ſeeds of theſe diſſentions, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſmall and weak in the beginning, for Peets, turves, devits, fold-dykes, poyndings, neighborlie marches, injurious words or light brawles, were then eaſilie to be ſetled, if diligence and authority had beene ioined for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing thereof, which being neglected by theſe to whom it appertained, theſe light jarres and inſolences did very oft kindle ſuch flames of diſorder, diſſention, rank or and feed, as in many yeeres with great ſtreames of bloud, deſolation and ruine of great and auncient houſes and races could hardlie be quenched. For remeed whereof his Maieſtie and eſtates foreſaids Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies and approoues the former act made by his Highnes for aboliſhing deadlie feeds in everie head, clauſe and artickle thereof. And farther ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and ordaines that in everie ſhyre within this kingdome there ſhall be yeerely appointed by his Maieſtie, ſome godlie, wife and vertuous gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of good quality, moyen and report, making reſidence within the ſame, in ſuch number as the bounds of the ſhyre ſhall require, to be Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for keeping his Maieſties peace, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Maieſty with adviſe of the Lords of his privie Counſel ſhal giue power &amp; commiſſion to overſe, try &amp; <pb facs="tcp:181030:6"/>prevent all ſuch occaſiones as may breed trouble and violence amongſt his Maieſties ſubiects, or forceable contempt of his Maieſties authoritie and breach of his peace: and to command all perſones in whom they ſhall ſee manifeſt intention to make trouble or diſorder, eyther by gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ydle and diſorderlie perſones, or by publict bearing or wearing of Piſtolets or other forbidden weapons, and ſuch other riotous &amp; ſwaggring behaviour: to binde themſelues and finde caution vnder competent paines to obſerue his Maieſties peace, and for their compearance before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Iuſtice or Lords of his privie Counſell, to vnderly ſuch order as ſhall be found convenient for puniſhing their tranſgreſſions or ſtaying of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and enormities: And if needs bees, to require the dewtifull and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſubiects of the ſhyre to concurre with them in preventing all ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temps and violences, or for taking or warding of the wilfull and diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent authors committers &amp; foſterers of theſe crimes &amp; diſorders vnder ſuch competent arbitrare paines as his Maieſtie and Lords of his privie Counſel ſhall appoint for the offenders, and ſuch of the countrie as being required ſhall not giue their ready and afolde concurrance to his Maieſties commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners in the premiſſes, whereby the ordinare magiſtrates &amp; officers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſhyres may be the better aſſiſted, and their abſence, imployments or other impediments more commodiouſlie ſupplied, without derogation of their iuriſdiction or want of readie comfort and iuſtice to the obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iects within the bounds thereof. Ordaining alſo the ſaids commiſſioners to giue trew advertiſement and information to the Lords of his Maieſties pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie Counſell, Iuſtice generall and his deputes, his Maieſties Theſaurer and other magiſtrates and officers whom it effeires, of the names of ſuch faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnſuſpect witneſſes and aſſyſſers to be ſommoned in all crimes and diſorders which ſhall happen to fall forth within the ſaids ſhyres, as ſhall be knowne to be moſt meete and able for tryall and probation of the ſame, and for eſchewing that ſuch as are either aged, ſicklie or vnable to travell, or ignorant of the facts to be tryed, be not vniuſtlie vexed or vnneceſſarly drawne from their owne houſes and effaires for matters wherein they are not able to give anie light.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <head>Act of the apparelles of Iudges, Magiſtrates and Church-men.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR Soveraine Lord and Eſtates of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment finding by daylie experiences that the greatnes of his Maieſties empyre, magnificence of his Court, fame of his wiſdome and iuſtice and of the civilitie of his ſubiects, hes already begun to allure divers foraine Princes and other ſtrangers of all eſtates to make more frequent repaire to this country nor ever they did in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie <pb facs="tcp:181030:7"/>preceeding age: which reſort of ſtrangers will by all appearance both continue and dayly more and more increaſe, and by them, no doubt report wil go through al the world of the eſtate &amp; governement of the kingdome according to the order which they ſhal ſee obſerved within the ſame: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the rules and good exemple flowing from the eſtates of Parliament and magiſtrates to the whole remanent ſubjects of the realme, It is moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare that ſuch gravitie and comelines be vſed by the Lords and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſares of Parliament, and other magiſtrates in their apparell &amp; behaueor as may beſt deſerue the good report and trew commendation of all Princes, Noble men &amp; other ſtrangers who ſhall haue occaſion to ſee &amp; relate the ſame. The reſpect whereof having induced his Maieſtie to preſcriue to the Nobility apparel for the Parliament beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming their honorable eſtate: And vnderſtanding that the remanent members of that high Court hes not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed themſelues to like conveniencie, neither yet that the courſe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his Maieſtie for diſcharging noble men and gentle men to be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Provoſts and magiſtrates of burrowes (whereof none ſhould be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but burgeſſes, actuall trafickers and inhabitants of the ſaids burrowes) hes taine ſuch effect as is moſt neceſſare for preſervation of the liberties &amp; good eſtate of the ſaids burrowes, &amp; hindring the diſſipation of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good and perverting of their priviledges. For remeede whereof his Maieſty with adviſe of the eſtates of his Hignes Parliament Statutes &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daines that no man ſhall in anie time comming be capable of Provoſtrie or other magiſtracie within anie burgh of this realme, nor to be elected to any of the ſaids offices within a burgh but marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; actuall trafickers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting within the ſaids burghes allanerlie, and no others. And that the ſaids magiſtrates of burrowes to be hereafter elected, and their commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of Parliament Shall haue and weare at Parliament conventions and other ſolemne times and meettings when the dignitie ſhall require it, ſuch comelie and decent apparell as his Maieſtie ſhall preſcriue convenient for their rank and eſtate, whereby they may be decemed from other common Burgeſſes, and be more reverenced by the people ſubiect to their charge. And becauſe a comelie, decent &amp; orderlie habite &amp; apparell in the Iudges of the land, is not onlie an ornament to themſelues (being a badge &amp; mark for diſtinguiſhing them from the vulgare ſort) but the ſame alſo breedes in common people that reverence and regarde that is dew and proper for men in theſe places: And this beeing a cuſtome vniverſallie obſerved almoſt throgh all Europe, The want whereof is much cenſured by ſtrangers reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in theſe parts. The ſaids eſtates therefore vpon infinite proofes they haue of his Maieſties moſt ſingulare wiſdome in all his directiones and of his gracious loue and affection to this his natiue kingdome. Haue in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie referred to his Highnes owne appointment The aſſigning of anie ſuch ſeverall ſort of habite and veſtiment as ſhall be in his Maieſties iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb facs="tcp:181030:7"/>moſt fitting &amp; proper, as well for Lords of Seſſion being the ſuprem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Iudges in civill actions, as for all other inferior Iudges of the like cauſes, as alſo for the criminall and Eccleſiaſticall Iudges, and for Advocates, Lawyers and all others living by law and practiſe thereof, that ſo everie one of theſe people may be knowen and dignoſced in their place, calling and function, and may be accordinglie regarded and reſpected. Attover his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie and eſtares foreſaids, conſidering what ſlander and contempt hes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſen to the Eccleſiaſticall eſtate of this kingdome by the occaſion of the light &amp; vndecent apparell vſed by ſome of that profeſſion, and chiefly theſe having vote in Parliament. It is therefore ſtatute that everie Preacher of Gods word ſhall hereafter weare blacke, graue and comelie apparell beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming men of their eſtate and profeſſion. As likewaies that all Pryors, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots and Prelates having vote in Parliament, and ſpeciallie Biſhops, ſhall weare graue and decent apparell agreable to their function, and as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their rank, dignity &amp; place. And becauſe the whole eſtates humbly &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfully acknowledges that God of his great mercie hes made the people and ſubiects of this countrie ſo happy as to haue a King raigne over vs who is moſt godly, wiſe and religious, haring al erroneous and vaine ſuperſtition, juſt in governement and of long experience therein, knowing better then anie King living what appertaines and is convenient for everie eſtate in their behaviour and dewtie. Therefore it is agreed and conſented to by the ſaids eſtates that what order ſo euer his Maieſtie in his great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall thinke fit to preſcriue for the apparell of Churchmen agreable to their eſtate &amp; moyen, The ſame being ſent in write by his Maieſtie to his Clarke of Regiſter, ſhall be a ſufficient warrand to him for inferting thereof in the books of Parliament, to haue the ſtrength and effect of an act there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with executorials of horning to be direct thervpon againſt ſuch perſons as within the ſpace of fourtie dayes after the publication or intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them of the ſaide act or charges vſed againſt them therevpon, ſhall not provide themſelues of the apparell to be appointed by his Maieſtie for men of their vocation and eſtate to be vſed and worne by them and their ſucceſſors at the times and in manner to be expreſſed in the ſaid Act to be made by his Highnes thereanent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <head>Act of skandalous ſpeeches and libels.</head>
            <p>OVr Soverain Lord foreſeing that there is nothing ſo neceſſare for the perpetuall well &amp; quietnes of al his ſubiects of this monarchy as the furtherance &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhment of the vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his two famous &amp; moſt ancient kingdomes of Scotland &amp; England, whereof his Maieſtie out of his fatherlie care of the peace and happines of his good &amp; faithfull people, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <pb facs="tcp:181030:8"/>moſt inſtantly &amp; earneſtly ſolicited the perfection, and by the aſſiſtance of the worthieſt members of both kingdomes ſo effectuallie advanced the ſame, as he hopes, God willing, in his raigne to ſee the wiſhed end of that great work, which in his royal perſon hes received ſo miraculous &amp; happy a beginning: And nevertheles finding therein ſuch malicious lettes as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell &amp; his ſuppoſts doe vſually ſuggeſt to the hinderance of al iuſt &amp; godlie interpriſes, Speciallie by the falſe &amp; calumnious brutes, ſpeeches &amp; writes craftily vttered &amp; diſperſed by ſome lawles &amp; ſouleles people of this realm, aſwell in private conferences as in their meettinges at tavernes, ailehouſes &amp; playes, &amp; by their paſquils, libels, rymes, cockalins, comedies &amp; ſuch like occaſions wherby they ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der maligne &amp; revile the people, eſtate &amp; country of England, and divers his Maieſties honorable Counſellors, magiſtrates &amp; worthy ſubiects of that his Maieſties kingdome: the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance wherof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to incenſe the people of England to iuſt grief &amp; miſcontentment, may not only hinder the intended vnion of all the good ſubiects of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, but ſtir vp in them ſuch irreconciliable evil wil, as with time might bring forth moſt dangerous &amp; harmeful effects. For remeede &amp; preventing whereof, his Maieſty remembring how ſtraite &amp; ſevere puniſhment hes by the lawes &amp; acts of his moſt royal progenitors kings of this realme hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bene ordained to be inflicted vpon ſuch as ſhould deviſe or vtter falſe &amp; ſlanderous ſpeeches &amp; writes to make diſſentions between the Prince &amp; his ſubiects, or raiſe ſedition in the realme, and conſidering that al ſuch purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; writes as may breed diſliking betweene the inhabitantes of the ſaids kingdomes of Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, being now al become his Maieſties liege-people, equally ſubiect and equally beloved of his Highnes, Tends to moſt dangerous diſſention &amp; ſedition amongs his ſubiects: Therfore his Maieſty with adviſe &amp; conſent of the whole eſtates of this Parliament, ſtatutes and ordaines, That who ſo ever ſhall hereafter by word or write deviſe, vtter or publiſh any falſe, ſlanderous or reprochfull ſpeeches or writes of the eſtate, people or countrie of England, or of any Counſellour thereof, tending to the remembrance of the ancient grudges borne in time of bypaſt troubles, (the occaſion whereof is now happilie aboliſhed by the bleſſed conjunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſaids kingdomes vnder his Maieſties ſoveraignity &amp; obedience) or to the hinderance of the wiſhed accompliſhment of the perfect vnion of the ſaids kingdomes, or to the ſlander or reproch of the eſtate, people or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of England, or diſhonor or prejudice of anie Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellor of the ſaid king dome, wherby hatred may be foſtered &amp; intertained or miſliking raiſed be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tweene his Maieſties faithfull ſubiects of this Ile. The authors of ſuch ſedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious, ſlanderous &amp; iniurious ſpeeches or writes or diſperſers thereof, after tryall taine of their offence, either before his Maieſties iuſtice or the Lords of his Highnes privie Counſell, ſhall be ſeverelie puniſhed in their perſons and goods, by inpriſonment, baniſhment, fyning or more rigorous corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <pb facs="tcp:181030:8"/>paine, as the qualitie of the offence ſhall be found to merite at his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties pleaſure: And all ſuch as hearing or getting knowledge of anie ſuch ſpeeches or writes, ſhal conceale the ſame, and not reveile them to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties ordinare officers, magiſtrats or Counſellors, wherby the authors and diſperſers thereof may be puniſhed, ſhal vnderly the like tryall &amp; paine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Act_of__Scottish_Parliament">
            <head>Act anent fugitiue perſones of the borders to the in-countrie.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as the Kings Maieſtie is reſolved to purge the middleſhires of this Ile heretofore called the borders of Scotland &amp; England of that barbarous cruelty, wickednes &amp; incivilitie which by inveterate cuſtom was almoſt become naturall to many of the inhabitants thereof, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to the knowledge, loue and feare of God, reverence of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties authority, obedience of his lawes and dutie to their nighbors: For acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of that moſt royall deſigne, made choſe of one to be Commiſſioner in theſe bounds, whom by manie aſſured proofes in former imployments of greateſt conſequence, his Maieſtie knew to be indued with all qualities ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for ſo weightie a charge: who following preciſelie the rules of his Maieſties moſt prudent directions, and vſing all poſſible diligence &amp; dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in proſecution thereof, made ſo happie progreſſe in that good courſe, as juſtlie puniſhing the moſt perverſed &amp; rebellious ringleaders (whoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendement was deſperate) and tranſporting others of them foorth of this Ile, the reſt were brought to verie ſetled quyetnes &amp; obedience of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties lawes, a verie few number of our-lawes onelie excepted, who being ſo earneſtly ſearched &amp; perſued in theſe bounds, as al hope of eſcaping &amp; lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger impunity was taine from them, they haue by moſt ſubtle &amp; crafty means of changing their names and diſſembling the place of their nativity, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyed themſelues in the in-countries of this realme, and inſinuated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſervice with Noble men &amp; others of good qualitie, not only there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by eſchewing their deſerved puniſhment, but alſo abuſing and harming his Maieſties good ſubiects by their darned ſtouths in the incountrie tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, reſet &amp; quyetly ſolde in the bounds of the late borders: And again ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling geare forth thereof &amp; out of the bounds of theſe middle-ſhires, &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; ſelling the ſame in the in-countries. Beſides that others of the ſaides outlawes haue beene allured &amp; had reſet &amp; overſight in the in-countries by ſome men of rank &amp; power to be inſtruments &amp; executors of ſuch revenge and miſcheefe againſt theſe to whom they beare malice, grudge or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, which for feare of his Maieſties lawes and authoritie they durſt not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt by themſelues. For remeede wherof his Maieſty with adviſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the eſtates of Parliament, Statutes and ordaines that no man ſhall hereafter either receiue or reteine anie man borne or long habituate in the late borders in his ſervice or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany or vpon his lands, vnles he haue certain <pb facs="tcp:181030:9"/>knowledge or a trew &amp; authentick teſtimonial of his Maieſties great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner of the late borders or his deputes, of the ſaid border-mans trew name and ſurname, place of his nativitie and report of his trueth and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and that he is no knowen malefactor, but repute a dewtifull &amp; obedient ſubiect, vnder the paine to incur the danger, and to be made anſwerable ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy and criminally to his Maieſtie and all his lawfull ſubiects for al actions and crimes which might be any waies laide to the charge of the ſaids bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken men, for anie cauſe or occaſion either proceeding or during the time of their receiuing or retaining them in their ſervice, company or vppon their lands, as if the reſetter had committed the ſaids faults himſelfe. As likewiſe becauſe ſome who are not knowen to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted any haynous offence in their owne perſone obtaining teſtimoniall of their name, birth &amp; good report may giue the ſame to broken men to be vſed by them in places where they are not knowen, It is ſtatute and ordained that whoſoever ſhall eyther giue his teſtimoniall to anie man, whereby it may be abuſed by another nor him to whom it was trewlie graunted, or who ſhall falſlie vie another mans teſtimoniall, or who ſhall fordge to himſelfe or vſe a falſe teſtimonial in the premiſſes, ſhall be puniſht to the death. And to the effect his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties faithfull and obedient ſubiects may haue the better knowledge of the ſaids fugitiues and broken men, and that ſuch as reſet them maye want all pretext and excuſe of ignorance, It is ſtatute and ordained that a Roll ſhall be made by his Maieſties great Commiſſioner of the middle ſhires, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the names of the ſaids rebels, fugitiues, outlawes &amp; broken men w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt notor &amp; evident marks &amp; deſcription of their age, ſtature, colour &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tokens whereby they may be moſt eaſilie and readily knowen. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imprinted ſhall be ſent to the ſhireffes and magiſtrates of the in-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and proclaimed at the market croſſes of the head burrowes of the ſhyres and other places needfull, And thereafter be publictlie affixed vpon the ſaids croſſes or tolbuithes of the ſaids burrowes. After which publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is ſtatute that the contraveners of this Act or anie head or artickle of the ſame ſhal be rigorouſlie puniſhed in their perſons and goods in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner foreſaid. <hi>Extractum de Libro Actorum Parliamenti per me Dominum</hi> Ioannem Skena <hi>de Curriehil militem, Clericum Regiſtri Conſilij &amp; rotulorum S. D. N. Regis, teſtantibus men ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; ſubſcriptione mamialibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:181030:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
